Finding aid to the Howard Madison Parshley Papers CA.MS.00064
Smith College Archives
Howard Madison Parshley Papers
1913-1991
Smith College Archives
Parshley, H. M. (Howard Madison), 1884-1953.
CA.MS.00064
1.042 linear feet (3 containers)
Professor, zoology, translator, The Second Sex. Contains, biographical information, articles, correspondence, photographs, published works, notes and translations. Notable correspondents include Adelaide Cromwell and Margaret Sanger.
Biographical / Historical
Howard Madison Parshley was a professor at Smith from 1917 until 1952, and the chairman of the Zoology Department for many years. His early specialization in entomology broadened to include studies of genetics, reproduction and human sexuality. At Smith he taught classes in general zoology, genetics/reproduction and entomology. His publications included books, reviews and more than 300 articles in scientific as well as nonscientific journals. His books include Science and Good Behavior, The Science of Human Reproduction, and A Survey of Biology. Parshley was recognized as an international authority on the Hemiptera-Heteroptera and was editor of the General Catalogue of the Hemiptera. Parshley wrote the screenplay and co-starred with Clarence Darrow, the well-known evolutionist of the Scopes trial, in the documentary film, "The Mystery of Life," which was filmed and released in 1931. His fellow faculty called him a "pioneer in the application of the scientific outlook to the behavior of man." A talented musician and music-lover, for decades he played the double bass in the Smith College Orchestra, in the Pioneer Valley Symphony and in the professional Springfield Symphony Orchestra.
Born to a pianist and a Baptist minister in Hallowell, Maine in 1884, Parshley grew up in eastern New York. With a strong classical education from the Boston Latin School (1901-1905) he went on to study at Harvard University, achieving an A.B. (1909), an A.M. (1910) and an Sc.D (1917). Concurrent with these studies Parshley also attended the New England Conservatory of Music. He married Nancy Fredricson in 1910. From 1911 to 1914 he taught zoology at the University of Maine in Orono. The Parshley's son, Thomas Fredricson Parshley was born in 1912 and their daughter, Elsa Parshley Brown, Smith '35 was born in 1914.
In 1917, Parshley accepted a position at Smith as assistant professor of zoology. He soon became professor and later chairman of the Department. He began translating into English what is now called "The Feminist Bible," Simone de Beauvoir's groundbreaking and controversial Le Deuxieme Sexe, in November 1949. During his work, he suffered a minor heart attack in 1952. Shortly after the publication of his translation of The Second Sex, and the completion of his translation of a French zoology book on mammals, Parshley died of a second heart attack on May 19, 1953. Parshley's translation of de Beauvoir's The Second Sex is still in print and widely used by Women's Studies programs throughout the English-speaking world.
[Biographical note prepared in cooperation with Elsa Parshley Brown]
Scope and Contents
Collection contains biographical information, articles, correspondence, photographs, published works, notes and translations. Notable correspondents include Adelaide Cromwell and Margaret Sanger.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical
II. Photographs
III. Correspondence
IV. Publications
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Second Sex manuscript and related materials were donated by Professor Parshley's daughter, Elsa Parshley Brown, Smith class of 1935. All other materials are from various sources at Smith College.
Parshley, H. M. (Howard Madison), 1884-1953.; Beauvoir, Simone de, 1908- Deuxieme sexe.; Smith College--Faculty.; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966.; Cromwell, Adelaide M., Class of 1940
- Series I. Biographical
  - Biographical, 1922-1988 (Box 963, Folder 1)
- SERIES II: Photographs
  - Photographs, undated (Box 963, Folder 2)
- SERIES III: Correspondence
  - Correspondence with family and associates, 1933-1991 (Box 963, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence on the translation of Le Deuxieme Sexe, Jul 1949 - Dec 1949 (Box 963, Folder 4)
  - Jan 1950 - Dec 1950 (Box 963, Folder 5)
  - Jan 1951 - Jun 1951 (Box 963, Folder 6)
  - Jul 1951 - Dec 1951 (Box 963, Folder 7)
  - Jan 1952 - Jun 1952 (Box 963, Folder 8)
  - Jul 1952 - Jan 1953 (Box 963, Folder 9)
  - Mar 1953 - Apr 1953 (Box 963, Folder 10)
- SERIES IV: Publications
  - Publications: A - G, 1913-1952 (Box 963.1, Folder 1)
  - Publications: H - Z, 1917-1949 (Box 963.1, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Reviews, 1918-1952 (Box 963.1, Folder 3)
  - Copy of Le Deuxieme Sexe by Simone de Beauvior, 1949 (Box 963.1, Folder 4)
  - The Second Sex: News clippings, miscellany, 1952 (Box 963.1, Folder 5)
  - The Second Sex: Publishing notes, 1952 (Box 963.1, Folder 6)
  - The Second Sex: Translation notes, 1951-1953 (Box 963.1, Folder 7)
  - The Second Sex: Manuscript: Book I, Preface and Part I, p.1-127, 1949-1953 (Box 963.1, Folder 8)
  - Book I, Part II, p.128-232, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 1)
  - Book I, Part III, Chap IX, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 2)
  - Book I, Part III, Chap X-XI, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 3)
  - Book II, Part I, Chap I, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 4)
  - Book II, Part I, Chap II, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 5)
  - Book II, Part I-II, Chap IV-V, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 6)
  - Book II, Part II, Chap VI-VII, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 7)
  - Book II, Part II, Chap VIII-X, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 8)
  - Book II, Part III, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 9)
  - Book II, Part IV, 1949-1953 (Box 963.2, Folder 10)
  - "The Mystery of Life": film poster, 1931 (Box OV)